[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is Sankhyātanikaya 3528, Adhīta Sutta, Fire Discourse, or often translated as the Fire Sermon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: One time, the Blessed One was dwelling in Gāyā, at Gāyā's head, with one thousand monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: There, the Blessed One addressed the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Monks, all is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: What monks is the all that is on fire?
[SPEAKER_00]: The I-monks is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forms are on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: I-consciousness is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: I-impression is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, that which I-impression causes to appear felt pleasant,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one thing, like, first thing to note here, it's, eh... things that are on fire, means fire is not in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you, you, eh... the eye, the forms and eye consciousness, the fire takes them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes them up through passion, through anger, through dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that the fire is in the eye or in the forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason I say this, it's because often, when people would say you have a sight that induces, I don't know, ill-will, anger, so it's on fire with aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hypothetically speaking, you blame the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Habitually, you sort of jump into the conclusion, into the assumption, that the aversion, the anger, is because of the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the anger takes up the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that anger, or lust, or dullness, that fire, takes that up as fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is then the fuel, or rather, sorry, we know what the fuel is, but what is the reason that the fire takes these things up?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the Buddha explains the reason is passion, anger and dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion often translated.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll explain later why we translate it as dullness here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's having passion, which means, ah, so passion is something you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Compassion is not in the sight, in the beautiful sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion is not in the in the ugly, disagreeable sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dullness, it's not in the neutral sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically something you choose to cultivate in regard to those sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the same, it's exactly the same principle that would be described for the five aggregates and the upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the five aggregates, pañca khandhā and pañcupādānakkhandhā, said upādāna is not in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the assumption is not in the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the desire and lust in regard to the five aggregates that the assumption is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: An assumption literally means taking things up for granted, assuming them, and that's what fire does, takes them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... you don't do... you don't take things up consciously, in a sense of... sorry, not... you don't take things up voluntarily or intentionally, that's the better word.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take them up as a result, or rather taking up is the result of you intentionally cultivating lust, aversion, cultivating passion, aversion, dullness, indolence, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you then... that's how it results.
[SPEAKER_00]: That those things become taken up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the fire sets in and starts to burn.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't just say no to fire, you can't just say no to the assumptions, you can't say no to upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we choose to translate as assumption, not... the word upādāna, we choose to translate as assumption, not as holding or attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of those things are something you can be clearly conscious of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm holding on to this, thus now I will choose to let it go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not intentional.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot intentionally choose to let it go, because you're not intentionally holding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're doing something else, intentionally, that's then directly resulting in upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly, like, the fundamental thing that you are responsible for, that is the determining the upādāna in regard to the five aggregates, is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, choosing to ignore certain nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just choose to turn a blind eye on a certain characteristics of your experience, usually the unpleasant ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, that's simultaneously resulting and determining the presence of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will assume things when you don't know them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't know whether it's like this, so you assume it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you find assumptions there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't sort of intentionally create them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, I shall assume so and so.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you just find yourself assuming so and so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you never questioned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never looked at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were always blind of the nature of that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you were assuming it rightly, the fact is you don't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason you don't know is because you never checked that assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the nature of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption in regard to the form, feeling, perception, intentions and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not this some great mystery of the aggregates that you need to reveal and discover.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simply ignoring certain fundamental characteristics of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ignoring the certain characteristics of the five aggregates, or ignoring the nature of the senses, means passion, aversion, dullness in regard to them, are the attitudes you choose to cultivate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, they are on fire because of what you do underneath, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you see a beautiful sight and you have passion in regard to it,
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you have to stop blaming the beautiful sight for the passion, have to take responsibility for the passion, and the only way to do that is to restrain acting out of that passion, habitually, straight away towards the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you restrain, once you feel the burning of the fire, the burning of the passion, or aversion, or even delusion, you get to realize, okay, so it's... it's underneath this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fire is something that I do, which results in me basically being liable to burn.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches create impressions on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that thing that's underneath is what the Buddha described with certain subtle attitudes of delighting in sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, welcoming sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, adhering to them, hoping for...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these little attitudes that you cultivate towards accepting the pleasant ones and rejecting the unpleasant ones, and you just assume that
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fine to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You assume that you're in a position to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You assume that it's that it's absolutely normal to when there is pleasant, you just go towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it's unpleasant, you go away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it's neutral, you just sort of be blind of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: be a bit dull and indolent in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that assumption is the direct cause, then, that these things are on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring the nature of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as the Buddha said, so how do you... how would you stop assuming that it's fine to adhere to these things, to reject these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you stop delighting in sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, or having... being averse?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you stop those attitudes?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would stop them by seeing the danger in doing so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there is actually danger in accepting the beautiful sight, in delighting in it, in being elated on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the danger is not in the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sight is not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye is not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the fire is not dangerous, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fire is just a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that are on fire means, oh, they're burning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a symptom of that underlying fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the danger of that fuel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the danger is in basically not seeing that welcoming, delighting, adhering, being elated on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That attitude is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why is it dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, you would ask.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because that which you delight in, is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which you're welcoming, hoping to last, hoping to come your way, and persist, and stay, and not leave you, is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you delight in sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, without simultaneously ignoring the fact that sight, sound, smell, taste, touches are not in your control?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, literally, inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like, oh, not in my control, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have life of their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't even know about you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are the one picking these things up with all this, like, emotional, eh... craving for pleasure and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you be able to delight to welcome these things without
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously ignoring that they're not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ignoring that these things are not in your control is a necessary basis for being able to delight, rejoice, be elated, welcome it, adhere to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, ah, not ignoring that these things are not in your control, means you will be unable to delight in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean you won't see things with your eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't recognize whether they're beautiful, agreeable or ugly and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That all stays the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means now you're not... you're being unable to ignore the nature, the context in which they appear, such as they're not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are subjected to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no say in their arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things that, again, you can think about theoretically and abstractly, but that won't work in the same sense if you think of it on the level of the actual, currently enduring sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, thoughts, the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, that's why we translate passa as pressure and impression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because these things arise on their own, and you run... they exercise pressure on you automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure, like pleasure, exercises pressure to, to, eh... to go towards it, to have more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain exercises pressure to get away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It pressures you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And neutral feeling exercises pressure towards, basically, ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being dull, mentally, sort of, unaware, unmindful, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not keeping that mental alertness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what neutral feeling pressures you towards, towards that dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we translate it as dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because delusion, it's sort of, again, it has certain connotations of this
[SPEAKER_00]: Something you're deluded about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you figure it out, you'll be deluded.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more of an attitude of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, passion is an attitude towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion is an attitude away from pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dullness is the attitude towards that neutral feeling that's kind of undistinguishable, really, by any means of pleasure or pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why recognition, then, that these things are not in your control, they're there of the nature to cease having a reason, they're impermanent, you cannot basically have them submit to your will, it's the other way around, will then make you not delight in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you know there is a beautiful sight, and if you know any second can be taken away, any second it can sort of intoxicate you and completely make you spiral out of control, for example, you would regard that thing as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't go near it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by regarding that, by seeing the danger in these things, the Buddha said, you will stop delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will stop welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by the way, when there is aversion, you also delight in your own attitude of trying to get rid of that aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You also accept that attitude for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you see that aversion has arisen on its own, it means, oh, it's uncomfortable, but I'm not saying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having arisen, it will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just it's impossible for it to not cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's enough for you to not be pressured by that aversion, if you maintain that context, especially if you clarify it further and further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by seeing the danger in the eye, seeing the danger in the forms,
[SPEAKER_00]: And same goes for all the other senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will stop delighting in it, you will stop being averse towards it, you will stop resisting it, and you will stop giving in to that mental indolence and dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: By stopping of those attitudes and those choices, you then remove that fuel for the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the fire will diminish.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you would see the same sight that used to fill your mind with passion or fill your mind with anger, that you'll be burning with, now there is no fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sight hasn't changed, the eyes haven't changed, the consciousness of that hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still aware of the same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What has changed now, is there is no necessary basis of your delighting in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, there is no fire being manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because fire needs the delight to... in order... fire needs the delight, as in fire needs passion, aversion, dullness, for it to burn.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to... it needs to fuel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the eye is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, that attitude of fire then takes any... whichever way you look, say, on the experience of, like, a disagreeable sight, something fills you... you've seen something that fills you with aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... the fire is there because of the aversion, not because of the eye, not because of the sight, not because of you being aware of the eye and the sight, not even because of the pressure that that sight exhibits on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fire is there because of desire, because of passion, because of aversion, because of delusion, because of dullness, whichever way you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, then, that fire takes up anything within that relationship, within the domain of sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the eye will be on fire, the sights will be on fire, everything in between will be on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, high consciousness will be on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure that that experience exhibits on you, impression created by that sight, will be on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that's felt on account of whatever you've seen, pleasant, unpleasant, neither unpleasant or pleasant, that's all on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what this states is that, through your unchecked delight, welcoming, assuming,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seeing the nature of the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch is not having reflected upon it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have accumulated the abundance of fire, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which now means that this fire is rolling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, once the big fire starts, it starts taking things up on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it becomes kind of self-sufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, for as long as there is eye, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as there are things to be taken up by fire, fire will take it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to diminish that fire, it's not enough for you to just nod delight in these things once, twice, three times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thousand times, you have to develop the attitude of perpetual non-delight, of perpetual non-resistance to pain, non-acceptance of pleasure, and not slipping into dullness on account of neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what will constitute that perpetual attitude?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that depends on the individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: For somebody, that might be done in a shorter period of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: For somebody, longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on average, you would assume it will take quite a while
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it took quite a while to accumulate that massive fire through your unchecked desires, passions, aversions and so on, things you've been acting out of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have developed that attitude,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of non-giving in to resistance to pain, acceptance of pleasure, and then acting out of it, you have basically, gradually, started removing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't just directly go head-on and extinguish the fire, but you can start removing that which fire can take up as fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And eventually, it will have to burn out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will burn out having not taking anything new as fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when the fire is extinguished.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where, literally, there's nothing else then to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, the eye, the sights, the nose, the smells, and so on, the mind, the thoughts remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And with that said, those things remain in Tathāgata as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the beautiful, recognizing beautiful things, recognizing ugly things, all that Tathāgata still has.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't lost preferences or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What Tathāgata doesn't have is the desire and lust
[SPEAKER_00]: in regard to his own thought, in regard to his perceptions, in regard to his sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by practicing, by discerning the danger in these things, you will prevent yourself from habitually choosing passion, choosing aversion, choosing dullness, giving in, cultivating, dwelling in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will prevent yourself from doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By preventing yourself from doing it, you are removing the basis for fire to keep finding fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, indirectly speaking, then, you are extinguishing the fire, which is kind of, in a way, a direct way of doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Removing the next thing the fire will take up, you know it will directly cause that fire to burn out, to stop, to disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's important to recognize here that the fire is on the basis of your attitude of passion, anger and dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: ill-will, aversion and dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in the eye, in the sight, in the consciousness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the same goes, the sutta carries on for all the other senses, including the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is on fire, phenomena are on fire, mind consciousness is on fire, mind impression is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which mind impression causes to appear, felt pleasant or painful, neither painful nor pleasant, that is also on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: On fire with what?
[SPEAKER_00]: On fire with passion, with anger, with dullness, with birth, aging, death, subtle limitation, pain, grief and despair.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this carries on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just piling up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's on fire with passion, with anger, with dullness, because you delight in it, you don't see danger in it, which then means you... on account of that fire, it's on fire with birth, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means birth, aging, death, all these things that are affecting sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, mind and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they pertain to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they are exhibiting pressure on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are liable to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are subject to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Accepting things that are born, that are aging, that are dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body, the senses, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another layer then, on piling up, is sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief, despair.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means any sorrow, any lamentation, any pain, any grief, any despair, on account of anything in this life, it's not specific.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair is because you make yourself liable to it, because you make yourself... because you cultivate passion, anger and dullness in regard to completely unrelated things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might be passionate about one thing and then suffer on account of something completely, seemingly unrelated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because there is passion present in experience, you're liable to suffering on account of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's hard to approve these things, and it takes a constant repetition, because you cannot see a direct connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you could immediately see things you're passionate about, how the pain can result there, right away, written immediately, it would be easy to restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that connection is covered up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just rejoicing in a beautiful sight of a familiar person, or a person you love, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, why is that bad?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in itself it's not bad, but having an underlying attitude of passion towards that feeling you experience on account of that sight, that's mean, those impressions, whatever they cause to appear, that's felt pleasant, unpleasant or neutral,
[SPEAKER_00]: You delight in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have passion towards that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have anger towards the unpleasant feeling, or dullness towards neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, because the passion is present, or anger, or dullness, you are then liable to any type of suffering when things change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as the Buddha would say, being united with things you don't want, and separated from things you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: In brief, the five aggregates of your experience, like your experience as a whole, being affected by assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming yes, assuming no, assuming neither yes nor no, giving in to those attitudes, not being mindful about them, and basically cultivating passion, aversion, and dullness in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you are liable to
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair, absolutely regardless of specific things that might cause, that might trigger, let's say like that, those unpleasant states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the ultimate understanding of the Four Noble Truths is that suffering is determined by craving, not by anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, presence of craving in your experience, which is manifested through passion, manifested through anger, manifested through aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of craving means presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the two sides of the same coin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is one side, suffering is the other side.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a separate coin.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not craving arises first and then suffering follows.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of craving means presence of suffering, even if you don't see it, because you're looking on this coin side of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you get to know that suffering is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The liability to suffering, which is suffering in itself, is there because of craving, not because you've seen something disagreeable and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, craving equals suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving means suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you could also say, in the relation to this sutta, craving means fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have the attitude of craving on account of feeling that's impressed upon you,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the attitude of either passion, either anger, or either dullness, three modes through which craving manifests itself, or... and perpetuates itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of craving, you are then sorrowing, lamenting, in pain, in grieving, sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove craving,
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot sorrow, lament, pain, nor be grieving, nor be desperate, nor kind of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's the worst possible misfortune comes your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those things cannot be the reason for the presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things can then just be taken up by a fire, by passion, by suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the suffering is not in there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what the Buddha means here, furthermore, in that sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying thus, monks, well-learned, noble disciple, means at least a sotāpanna, means one who has developed the right view that, ah, craving means suffering, not the sights that I've seen that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving means suffering, not the sights that I've seen that cause passion in me and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Four Noble Truths, it's basically one insight, which means presence of craving equals presence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of craving, absence of suffering, even if the circumstances haven't changed, if it's all the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only thing that changes is absence of craving, means you will not suffer, even if it's the circumstances that used to make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having understood that, you then become wary of the I.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wary of the forms and eye consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wary of the domain of sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any impression the sights can have on you, you realize, well, anything I see, hear, smell, taste, touch, it exercises pressure on me, which, if I am not mindful of, let's say like that, means I will give in to craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll basically carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I better not cultivate that careless attitude towards the I-forms, I-consciousness and I-impression.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being wary of the I, wary of the forms, not because I and forms are to blame, but because, well, basically, you're an addict of passion, addict of aversion, addict of dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that addiction is in you, but in order to start uprooting it, you need to be wary of those things that you go for.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this case, it's the sights in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like in the beginning, yeah, you restrain this sight on account of that sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But eventually, with your reflection and contemplation and meditation, you arrive at any sight means any pressure means any possibility of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you want to be wary of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in other words, you want to stop welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop looking forward to the prospect of pleasing sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop looking forward to the prospect of avoiding the displeasing sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it means you become wary of the eye, the forms, the eye consciousness, and anything that those things... any way those things can impress you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's whatever's felt on account of it, pleasant, painful, neither pleasant nor... neither painful nor pleasant, you become wary of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wary of whatever you're currently feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Worry of whatever you're currently feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are, say, wary of the present enduring feeling of pleasure, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pleasure is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not trying to deny, trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're wary of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to blindly, carelessly, just crave for it and act out of that craving and give in to desire and lose your sense restraint?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through being wary of the I,
[SPEAKER_00]: The forms, the experience of the sight, the eye consciousness, the pressure that's felt on account of it... Oh, now you're wary of how you feel on account of it, which means you're automatically wary of all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by being wary of it, you will not give in to craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not giving in to craving, you cannot then perpetuate passion, aversion and dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without those things, fire cannot spread itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It runs out the fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you're wary of the sight, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, the point is to bring you back to be wary of whatever's presently enduring on the level of the feeling, whatever's currently felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either pleasant, or if it's felt unpleasantly, or neither pleasantly nor unpleasantly, you're wary of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're wary of that, you cannot crave towards any of that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot lean towards pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot lean away towards unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot, sort of, lean into indolence and dullness on account of neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simply by understanding where the problem is, which is what the right view is, you then get to exercise, so to speak, these attitudes correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the pleasant feeling, you get to exercise the non-leaning in the pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the unpleasant feeling, by being wary of the unpleasant feeling, you don't automatically lean away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start exercising non... or rather the absence of leaning away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant in that... in the verse.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, like, oh, if you... if you kind of fight the waves, if you go... if you go against them, you'll sink.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you try to go backwards, it will... it will...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you fight the waves, you get tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you go backwards, you get swept away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you try and stand still, you... you would sink.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how did you then cross the... the... to the other shore, they asked the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, well, I crossed it by not fighting the waves, by not pulling backwards and by not standing still.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by not leaning towards pleasant feeling, by not leaning away towards unpleasant feeling, and by not being sort of sinking into dullness towards neutral feeling, that's how you will remove the passion, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point there is that you need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like, oh, I will never lean towards anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't lean towards anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only lean, on that emotional level, towards things that are agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you don't lean towards things that are agreeable, but then you should maybe lean towards things that are disagreeable, because habitually you're leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, simply by leaning back towards the disagreeable, you stop leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, yeah, okay, you can then double down and start leaning, like self-mortification, but that's when you don't have the context of to what extent it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why this applies to the noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you know that you lean only
[SPEAKER_00]: for the disappearance of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the way, craving means leaning towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leaning away from pain, craving is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're leaning towards pleasure, lean away sufficiently enough for craving to disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't have that as a criteria, the disappearance of craving, is the measure where you stop leaning away from pleasure, you then lean away too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the simile... we mention that often, that... the deer herd, the simile of bait, sotā, in Madhyamanikāya.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is when the deer herd realizes, oh, this pleasure, sense pleasures, are basically a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're a bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, they shun it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They lean away, not just from the bait, but they lean away from anything agreeable, anything that comes from the domain where the bait is, which is why, then, they starve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the other one is sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: You're completely careless about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is sort of denying it too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I'm describing here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the attitude of habitually just having an experience of pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're leaning towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will lean towards it if you're not wary of that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, becoming wary of the feeling, you stop leaning towards it habitually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, you might lean away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Compensate for the amount you were leaning forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same in the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You habitually in a way, which means sometimes you might need to lean forward, just to regain the perspective on that unpleasant feeling and counter the habitual leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't use it as a rule of thumb that I will always lean away from unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no reason to lean away from pleasant feeling if you haven't been leaning towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes you don't lean towards pleasure even when you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you just take it as a rule of thumb, that you will always lean away from pleasure, and always lean towards pain, to counter your craving, means you're doing it blindly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will only correspond rightly sometimes, and you're not developing wisdom on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when people basically start blaming sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, for things they feel, and for the craving on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, they simply think that if they avoid certain sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, they're avoiding the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might still well be leaning towards that internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Welcoming, delighting, accepting, assuming that attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the middle way is recognizing where the problem is of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that will determine whether you lean towards or lean away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if you're caught in constant denial of any pleasure, even pleasure you don't crave for,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're overdoing the leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not having the middle ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing where the craving is, because craving can only be manifested in the middle ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding, then, the weariness of the sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, creates a basis for you to discern where that craving is, where the necessary condition for passion, aversion and dullness is, on account of which there is all this fire of your senses, that they're burning up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would be wary of the eye, not simply by, you know, being mindful of what you're seeing, and what you're hearing, and so on, and attending to it, and try not to lose focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can that possibly result in you being wary of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're wary of it when you start looking into its nature, discerning the nature of sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said before, these are things that I'm subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not in their control.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're literally...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm oppressed by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: My sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot stop seeing, smelling, tasting, hearing and touching and thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do I still act and hold the view and attitude as if they're mine and in my control, when I absolutely no say in them?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start thinking like that, and you have to keep repeating those reflections, and drilling them in, and clarifying them more, and more, and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how discernment takes place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you are developing the attitude of wariness towards the eye, and forms, nose, and smells, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by being wary, you'll be unable to be careless, leaning toward, carelessly leaning away, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: By being wary, as a basis, you then will be unable to crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not craving, you'll be unable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's amidst the things that used to cause you to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there he says it, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being wary, he becomes dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being wary, no basis for craving, no basis for craving, no basis for passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, without passion, you really get to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fire... the smoke's gone, because the fire stopped burning, and now you see clearly what things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the... as he says here, he becomes... he becomes dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dispassionate, he's liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're liberated from that self-perpetuating fire that you kept providing unintentionally... kept providing fuel for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with liberation, you know that you are liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vimuttasmiṁ vimuttam iti.
[SPEAKER_00]: With liberation, it is liberated, jñāna hoti, the knowledge manifests.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's important to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the liberation will happen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had this special magical experience where all the fire disappeared and everything has ceased and now you're just enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know exactly that liberation came on account of this passion, that came on account of non-craving, that came on account of you discerning and drilling and training yourself in becoming wary of the sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, for which sensory strength was necessary beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you are liberated, you know you are liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge is recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, I am free.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not just that you are free from these things, you know what freedom is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is... With liberation, it is liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows, he understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, Arahant knows that he knows, and knows how he knows as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm just emphasizing that because, again, it's deeply rooted, obviously, in all what you kind of expect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if I just go through these motions and then this passion will occur and then enlightenment will happen and I'm fixed.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simply work and repetitive training, drilling and enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Patience, endurance, sense restraint and just reflection, reflection, reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meditation becomes then more composed form of the same reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is thinking and pondering then, in first jhāna, other than reflection, that is now fully withdrawn from any slightest basis of passion in regard to the sense pleasures?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, awareness will be developed on account of correct reflection, and correct reflection will be developed on account of correct instruction, and correct instruction will be developed on account of, well, correctly attending to what you hear that also happens to be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's two factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to find the right instructions, and you also need to attend to it correctly, because you might have been hearing the right instructions and disagreeing with it, or dismissing it, or not accepting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't been attending it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the first step of the right attention is to recognize your own position.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I know for myself what craving is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I, on account of which, I'm unable to suffer, like a noble disciple?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I an arhant?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, I mustn't dismiss any instruction that I come across, simply because of how it makes me feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time I should dismiss is after I have invested sufficient amount of effort where I understood that it's wrong and why it is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often you would see that, an attitude in yourself as well, you come across something and you just, oh no, this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so you had that attitude, you know, denying it, but now look at it and ask yourself, do I know why is this wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it simply because it displeases me or do I actually see a contradiction in it?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a flaw in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes, there is a flaw.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so what is the flaw?
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarify it, explain it to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you understand it, able to explain it, if you know that you know that there is a flaw, then fine, move on to the next instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more often than not, what people do is, you kind of go along, pick up these views, bump from one instruction to the other, pick up bits and pieces, never really thinking about or getting to the meaning of any of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just accumulating the pile and then
[SPEAKER_00]: It has some sort of a shape of a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, when you come across something that's very much perceived as against the view, you simply reject it, because it displeases you, it counters you, or so it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you understood it as wrong, and to what extent it was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the most perilous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of that attitude, of simply judging what instructions you will heed, an effort you make, because you don't look for the meaning behind the instruction, even the one that pleases you,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not be able to then develop that right reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the right reflection, you will not become weary of things, because you're not really discerning the nature you need to discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not becoming weary, you will not become dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not being dispassionate, you will not be liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not being liberated, you will not be able to say, oh, I'm liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down to
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, even if you're not a sotāpanna, because this, as we said, refers to sotāpanna, it's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: How am I feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I resisting my feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I rejecting these instructions that are upsetting me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I really refusing to hear them because they're displeasing me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it because... No, I've genuinely understood it's wrong for this reason, this reason and this reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you did understand, then you wouldn't be upset.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, if you understand fool as a fool, you cannot be upset with that fool.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time you're upset with fool is when he gets to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he gets to you when you don't understand why that happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you come across an instruction that you reject, that you say it's wrong, make sure you do it because you understood that it's wrong, not because it displeased you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is all nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, please explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nonsense means it's contradictory, it's nonsensical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explain it why, where, to what extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are able to see that, clearly,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can reject that and there will be no room for passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we explained, reading this sutta, passion is a result of your craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're passionately rejecting this view, means your passion... basically, underneath that, you're craving against the displeasure of that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where your argument is rooted in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where your attitude is rooted in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a very dangerous place to be in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you could well be rejecting the clearest, purest instruction that you could otherwise understand and become an arahant yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not saying you must then accept... Well, I mean, it's clear what I'm saying, but I just want to repeat it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about I mustn't reject and I must accept every instruction because I don't know which one's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must use your discernment, your reflection, and make sure you're not rooted in simply how it made you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to get to the bottom, and you need to understand the meaning of that instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's wrong, you need to see why it's wrong, and then you can move on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you will not just be acting out of your feeling, which will then... which is then preventing you from getting to understand the nature of acting out of your feeling, which is what craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, eh... this sort of, eh... ends up
[SPEAKER_00]: By saying that the monks that were there, they were pleased with the Blessed One's Word, they delighted in them, positively, and while this explanation was being given, those thousand monks, through non-assuming, their mind liberated, became liberated from art flows.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through non-craving, non-passion, they stopped assuming the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stopped assuming control of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stopped taking them up as mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stopped putting themselves first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, upādāna has been completely dispelled in regard to the five aggregates, on account of removing the craving in how you're feeling right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, these monks, they were listening this and became arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were obviously noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...of various degrees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, not just that it immediately made sense with this, the context that was resulting on account of making sense of what the Buddha was describing, was sufficient for their minds to become fully established upon that knowledge of liberation through dispassion, through being wary of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why I emphasize that now is because, just reading the last bit, you might just assume, oh, they just heard the Buddha and boom!
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahantship happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've done all the work that the Buddha said here, in these few sentences.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've done that beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they were here, listening to the Buddha, they just got reminded of the context of non-craving, non-leaning towards, non-leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just got hammered in to the point of, oh, yeah, the holy life has been lived, done what should be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't lean towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't lean towards pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't lean towards... towards the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't lean into dullness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why then there were arahants.